<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?rfc linefile="1:draft-bryan-ftp-hash-04.xml"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc
  PUBLIC "" "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-bryan-ftp-hash-04" ipr="trust200902">
    <front>        
      <title abbrev="FTP Extensions for Cryptographic Hashes">FTP Extensions for Cryptographic Hashes</title>
      <author initials="A." surname="Bryan" fullname="Anthony Bryan">
	    <organization></organization>
	    <address>
		  <postal>
			<street></street>
		    <city>Pompano Beach</city>
			<region>FL</region>
			<country>USA</country>
		  </postal>
	      <email>anthonybryan@gmail.com</email>
	      <uri>http://www.metalinker.org</uri>
	    </address>
      </author>
      <author initials="T." surname="Kosse" fullname="Tim Kosse">
	    <organization></organization>
	    <address>
	      <email>tim.kosse@filezilla-project.org</email>
	      <uri>http://filezilla-project.org/</uri>
	    </address>
      </author>
      <author initials="D." surname="Stenberg" fullname="Daniel Stenberg">
	    <organization></organization>
	    <address>
	      <email>daniel@haxx.se</email>
	      <uri>http://www.haxx.se/</uri>
	    </address>
      </author>
	<date year="2010"/>        

      <abstract>
	<t>The File Transfer Protocol does not offer any method to verify the integrity of a transferred file, nor can two files be compared against each other without actually transferring them first. Cryptographic hashes are a possible solution to this problem. In the past, several attempts have been made to add commands to obtain checksums and hashes,
       however none have been formally specified, leading to non-interoperability and confusion. To solve these issues, this document specifies a new FTP command to be used by clients to request cryptographic hashes of files.
</t>
      </abstract>    
	  
  </front>    

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
	<t>The File Transfer Protocol <xref target="RFC0959"/> does not offer any method to verify the integrity of a transferred file, nor can two files be compared against each other without actually transferring them first. Cryptographic hashes are a possible solution to this problem. In the past, several attempts have been made to add commands to obtain checksums and hashes,
       however none have been formally specified, leading to non-interoperability and confusion. To solve these issues, this document specifies a new FTP command to be used by clients to request cryptographic hashes of files.
HTTP has a similar feature named Instance Digests <xref target="RFC3230"/> which allows a client to request the cryptographic hash of a file.</t>

      <t>[[ Discussion of this draft should take place on ftpext@ietf.org (or apps-discuss@ietf.org if necessary). ]]</t>
	  
      <section title="Example"><t><figure> 
	  <preamble>Example of HASH client request:</preamble>
	  
	  <artwork type="example">
        C&gt; HASH filename.ext
</artwork></figure></t>

<t><figure> 
	  <preamble>HASH server response with Positive Completion code and the requested hash using the currently selected algorithm:</preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">
        S&gt; 213 80bc95fd391772fa61c91ed68567f0980bb45fd9
</artwork></figure></t>
	  
    </section>
	</section>

      <section title="Notational Conventions"> 

	<t>This specification describes conformance of FTP Extensions for cryptographic hashes.</t>
     

	<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
	"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
	document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14, <xref target="RFC2119"/>, as scoped to those conformance targets.</t>
	
	<t>In examples, the "C&gt;" lines are commands from user-PI to server-PI, and the "S&gt;" lines are server-PI replies.</t>
	
	<t>This document also uses notation defined in STD 9, <xref target="RFC0959"/>.
	In particular, the terms "reply", "user", "file", "pathname", "FTP commands", "user-PI", "server-FTP process",
    "server-PI", "mode", "type", and "ASCII", are all used here as defined there.</t>

	<t>Syntax required is defined using the Augmented BNF defined in <xref target="RFC5234"/>.</t>

      </section>

	  
<section title="The HASH Command (HASH)" anchor="HASH">
<t>A new command "HASH" is added to the FTP command set to request the cryptographic hash of a file from a server-FTP process.</t>
<t>The syntax for the HASH command is:

<figure> 
	  <preamble></preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">
        hash-command = "HASH" SP &lt;pathname&gt;
</artwork></figure></t>
   
<t>As with all FTP commands, the "HASH" command word is case independent, and MAY be specified in any character case desired.</t>
   
<t>The HASH command keyword MUST be followed by a single space (ASCII 32) followed by the pathname.</t>

<t>The pathname argument should reference the same file as other file based commands such as STOR or RETR which the same argument would reference.</t>

<t>The text returned in response to the HASH command MUST be:</t>

<t><figure> 
	  <preamble></preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">
        hash-response = "213" SP 1*HEXDIGIT CRLF
</artwork></figure></t>

<t>All hash values MUST be encoded in lowercase hexadecimal format.</t>


<t>The HASH command is meant to be used for files transmitted in Image
type mode (TYPE I) and Stream transfer mode (MODE S). The returned hash
MUST be calculated over the raw octet data of the file irrespective of
the selected data type, transfer mode or any other state affecting the
transfer. In other words, if a client were to download a full file using
TYPE I and MODE S and were to calculate the hash on the received octet
data, it would be identical to the hash returned by HASH.</t>


<section title="User-PI usage of HASH">

<t>The user-PI issues the FEAT command to query the server-PI about which algorithm is currently selected. This also reveals the other algorithms that the server supports. In this example, the SHA-1 algorithm is currently selected.</t>

<t><figure> 
	  <preamble></preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">
        C&gt; FEAT
        S&gt; 211-Extensions supported:
        S&gt;  ...
        S&gt;  HASH SHA-256;SHA-512;SHA-1*;MD5
        S&gt;  ...
        S&gt; 211 END
</artwork></figure></t>

<t>OPTS HASH is an alternative method for the user-PI to query the server-PI about which algorithm is currently selected.
<figure>
	  <preamble></preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">
        C&gt; OPTS HASH
        S&gt; 200 SHA-1
</artwork></figure></t>

<t>In this example, we wish to select SHA-256, a different algorithm.
<figure>
	  <preamble></preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">
        C&gt; OPTS HASH SHA-256
        S&gt; 200 SHA-256
</artwork></figure></t>

<t>The user-PI requests the cryptographic hash of a file with HASH command. Server-PI replies with cryptographic hash of file.
<figure>
	  <preamble></preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">
        C&gt; HASH filename.ext
        S&gt; 213 f0ad929cd259957e160ea442eb80986b5f01...
</artwork></figure></t>

<t>Client downloads file. Client hashes the downloaded file and compares its hash to the hash obtained from the server. The HASH command could also be used to verify that an uploaded file is an exact copy.</t>

</section>

<section title="Changing the HASH algorithm">

	<t>To query the current hash algorithm and to change it, the OPTS command as defined in <xref target="RFC2389"/> is used with HASH as the first argument. If no second argument is passed, OPTS HASH simply returns the currently selected hash algorithm. To change the algorithm, a valid hashtype MUST be given as second argument. If the command is successful, all future calls to HASH until the next successful OPTS HASH command or until the session is reinitialized (REIN) will use the selected hash algorithm.</t>
	
<t><figure>
	  <preamble></preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">
        C&gt; OPTS HASH
        S&gt; 200 SHA-1
        C&gt; OPTS HASH SHA-512
        S&gt; 200 SHA-512
        C&gt; OPTS HASH CRC-37
        S&gt; 501 Unknown algorithm, current selection not changed
</artwork></figure></t>

<t><figure> 
	  <preamble></preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">	
        hashopts-cmd = "OPTS HASH" [ SP hashtype ] CRLF
        hashopts-response = "200" SP hashtype CRLF
</artwork></figure></t>

</section>

<section title="FEAT Command Response for HASH Command">

<t>A server-FTP process that supports the HASH command MUST include, in the response to the FEAT command <xref target="RFC2389"/>, a feature line indicating that the HASH command is supported, along with a list of all supported hash algorithms in a semicolon separated list. The hash algorithm that is currently selected MUST be marked with an asterisk. The order of hash algorithms is insignificant. This command word is
   case insensitive, but it SHOULD be transmitted in upper case only. That is, the response SHOULD be:</t>

<t><figure> 
	  <preamble></preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">
        C&gt; FEAT
        S&gt; 211-Extensions supported:
        S&gt;  ...
        S&gt;  HASH SHA-256;SHA-512;SHA-1*;MD5
        S&gt;  ...
        S&gt; 211 END
</artwork></figure></t>

<t>The ellipses indicate place holders where other features MAY be listed, but this is OPTIONAL. The single space indentation of each feature line is REQUIRED by <xref target="RFC2389"/>.</t>

<t>The IANA registry named "Hash Function Textual Names" defines values for hash types. Hash names should be presented in uppercase, but comparisons should be case-insensitive, e.g. MD5, md5, Md5 are all the same.</t>

<t><figure> 
	  <preamble></preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">	
        hash-feat = SP "HASH" SP hashlist CRLF
        hashlist = 1*( hashname ["*"] ";" )
        hashname = 1*( hchar )
        hchar = ALPHA / DIGIT / "-" / "_" / "/" / "." / ","

</artwork></figure></t>

</section>

<section title="HASH Command Errors">

<t>The server-PI SHOULD reply with a 500 reply if the HASH command is unrecognized or unimplemented.</t>

<t>The server-PI SHOULD reply with a 501 reply to the OPTS HASH command if the user-PI has requested an unknown or unsupported algorithm.</t>

<t>The server-PI SHOULD reply with a 550 reply if the HASH command is used on a file that can not be found.</t>

<t>The server-PI SHOULD reply with a 552 reply if the user is not allowed to use the HASH command.</t>

<t>The server-PI SHOULD reply with a 450 reply if the server is busy, e.g. already hashing other files yet inviting the client to retry in future.</t>

</section>

</section>


	<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="IANA">
	<t>This new command is added to the "FTP Commands and Extensions" registry created by <xref target="RFC5797"/>.</t>
	<t>Command Name: HASH</t>
	<t>Description: Cryptographic Hash of a file</t>
	<t>FEAT String: HASH</t>
	<t>Command Type: Service execution</t>
	<t>Conformance Requirements: Optional</t>
	<t>Reference: This specification</t>


   
	</section>

<section title="Implementation Requirements">

	<t>All conforming implementations MUST at least support the SHA-1 algorithm <xref target="FIPS-180-3"/>. Implementations SHOULD NOT make any algorithm the default that is known to be weaker than SHA-1. Support for any additional algorithms is OPTIONAL.</t>


	</section>
	
	  <section title="Security Considerations">

<t>Calculating a file's hash is a CPU intensive operation and can easily
consume the available disk I/O resources. If the HASH command isn't
implemented carefully, a server could be vulnerable to a denial of
service attack. On an affected server a malicious user could, for example,
continuously send HASH commands over multiple connections and thus
consume most of the FTP server's CPU and disk I/O resources, leaving little room for other
operations.
To mitigate this risk, a server SHOULD cache the calculated hashes so
that the hash of a file is only calculated once even if multiple hash
requests are sent for that file.</t>

<t>The performance of commonly used hard disk drives is adversely affected
by the amount of time the device needs to reposition its read-and-write
heads. A server SHOULD therefore avoid hashing multiple files at the
same time which are located on the same physical media and SHOULD
instead hash them sequentially. The FTP server's right to refuse to calculate the hash is of course important to help against DOS risks. A possible solution is to use the 450
reply code of HASH to indicate that the server is already busy with
another HASH operation.</t>

<t>In addition, the HASH command can be used to draw conclusions about the
contents of a file. If the hash of a file on some server matches the
hash of some known, local file, both files are likely identical. To
prevent this scenario it suffices to limit use of the HASH command to
users who would already be able to download the file.</t>

<t>Currently, some of the hash types defined in the IANA registry named
"Hash Function Textual Names" are considered insecure.  These include
the whole Message Digest family of algorithms that are not suitable
for cryptographically strong verification.  Malicious people could
provide files that appear to be identical to another file because of
a collision, i.e., the weak cryptographic hashes of the intended file
and a substituted malicious file could match.</t>
		
	  </section>
	  


	</middle> 

	<back> 
	  
	  <references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor="RFC0959">

<front>
<title>File Transfer Protocol</title>
<author initials="J." surname="Postel" fullname="J. Postel">
<organization/></author>
<author initials="J." surname="Reynolds" fullname="J. Reynolds">
<organization/></author>
<date year="1985" month="October"/></front>

<seriesInfo name="STD" value="9"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="0959"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC2119">

<front>
<title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
<organization>Harvard University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
<street>Cambridge</street>
<street>MA 02138</street></postal>
<phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
<email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address></author>
<date year="1997" month="March"/>
<area>General</area>
<keyword>keyword</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
   In many standards track documents several words are used to signify
   the requirements in the specification.  These words are often
   capitalized.  This document defines these words as they should be
   interpreted in IETF documents.  Authors who follow these guidelines
   should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document:

<list>
<t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      RFC 2119.
</t></list></t>
<t>
   Note that the force of these words is modified by the requirement
   level of the document in which they are used.
</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC2389">

<front>
<title>Feature negotiation mechanism for the File Transfer Protocol</title>
<author initials="P." surname="Hethmon" fullname="P. Hethmon">
<organization/></author>
<author initials="R." surname="Elz" fullname="R. Elz">
<organization/></author>
<date year="1998" month="August"/></front>

<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2389"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC5234">

<front>
<title>Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title>
<author initials="D." surname="Crocker" fullname="D. Crocker">
<organization/></author>
<author initials="P." surname="Overell" fullname="P. Overell">
<organization/></author>
<date year="2008" month="January"/></front>

<seriesInfo name="STD" value="68"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5234"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="FIPS-180-3">
<front>
<title>Secure Hash Standard (SHS)</title>
<author>
    <organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST)</organization>
</author>
<date year="2008" month="October"></date>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="FIPS PUB" value="180-3"></seriesInfo>
</reference>

	  </references>


	  <references title="Informative References">

<reference anchor="RFC3230">

<front>
<title>Instance Digests in HTTP</title>
<author initials="J." surname="Mogul" fullname="J. Mogul">
<organization/></author>
<author initials="A." surname="Van Hoff" fullname="A. Van Hoff">
<organization/></author>
<date year="2002" month="January"/></front>

<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3230"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC5797">

<front>
<title>FTP Command and Extension Registry</title>
<author initials="J." surname="Klensin" fullname="J. Klensin">
<organization/></author>
<author initials="A." surname="Hoenes" fullname="A. Hoenes">
<organization/></author>
<date year="2010" month="March"/></front>

<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5797"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="draft-twine-ftpmd5">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="The MD5 and MMD5 FTP Command Extensions">The MD5 and MMD5 FTP Command Extensions</title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Twine" fullname="James Twine">
	  <organization></organization>
      <address><email>jtwine@jrtwine.com</email></address>
    </author>
    <date month="May" year="2002"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-twine-ftpmd5-00"/>
</reference>

	    </references> 

	    <section title="Acknowledgements and Contributors">
		  <t>Thanks to John C. Klensin, Alfred Hoenes, James Twine, Robert McMurray, and Mathias Berchtold.</t>
    </section>

	    <section title="List of Non-standard Cryptographic Hash or Checksum Commands and Implementations">
		<t>[[ to be removed by the RFC editor before publication as an RFC. ]]</t>
<t>A number of similar checksum or hash commands exist, but are not formally specified, leading to non-interoperability and confusion. The commands, any specifications, and relevant details:</t>
	    <t>
	    <list style="symbols">
<t>CKSM: GridFTP v2 Protocol Description http://www.ogf.org/documents/GFD.47.pdf Usage: OPTS CKSM &lt;algorithm&gt; CRLF. Supports ADLER32, MD5, CRC32.</t>
<t>MD5/MMD5: Expired Internet Draft <xref target="draft-twine-ftpmd5"/> from 2002. Usage: MD5 &lt;filepath&gt; Algorithm specific command. Response codes: 251 positive completion, 500 Command Not Recognized, 502 Command Not Implemented, 504 Command Not Implemented for the Specified Argument.</t>
<t>SITE CHECKSUM: Usage: SITE check_login SP CHECKSUM SP pathname CRLF. Supports CRC32 and MD5.</t>
<t>SITE SHOHASH: Usage: site shohash [filename]. Supports MD5. Response codes: 200 positive completion.</t>
<t>XCRC: By GlobalSCAPE in 2001. http://help.globalscape.com/help/secureserver2/File_Integrity_Checking.htm Usage: XCRC &lt;filename&gt; SP EP. SP is starting point and EP is ending point in bytes and are optional parameters. Algorithm specific command. Response codes: 250 positive completion, 450 Requested file action not taken. (File is busy), 550 Requested action not taken. (File not found, no read permission, SP or EP not correct).</t>
<t>XMD5: XMD5 &lt;filename&gt; SP EP. Similar to XCRC. Algorithm specific command.</t>
<t>XSHA, XSHA1, XSHA256, XSHA512: Usage similar to XCRC, although SP/EP usage unknown. Algorithm specific commands.</t>
	    </list></t>

<t>An incomplete list of FTP clients and servers that have implemented these commands:</t>
	    <t>
	    <list style="symbols">

<t>Akamai NetStorage (supports SITE CHKHSH/SITE SHOHASH) p17-18 http://pigdogslow.dyndns.org/NetStorage_UserGuide.pdf</t>
<t>Apache Ftp Server (supports MD5/MMD5 from draft-twine-ftpmd5) http://cwiki.apache.org/FTPSERVER/documentation.html</t>
<t>Backup4all Pro (supports XCRC)</t>
<t>Backup to FTP (supports XCRC)</t>
<t>BlackMoon FTP Server (supports XCRC) http://www.blackmoonftpserver.com/portal/readmore/features.html</t>
<t>C.P.A. Secure (supports XCRC) http://www.cpasecure.com/CPASecureVsSecureFTP.html</t>
<t>Cerberus FTP server (supports XCRC, XMD5, XSHA1, XSHA256, XSHA512) http://www.softpedia.com/progChangelog/Cerberus-FTP-Server-Changelog-1904.html</t>
<t>Core FTP Pro (supports XCRC)</t>
<t>Cross FTP Server (supports MD5/MMD5)</t>
<t>FileCOPA FTP Server (supports XCRC, XMD5, XSHA1) http://www.filecopa-ftpserver.com/features.html</t>
<t>File Watchdogs FTP Server (supports XCRC, XMD5, XSHA1, XSHA256, XSHA512) http://www.filewatchdogs.com/ftpsitehosting/help/15559.htm</t>
<t>FireFTP (supports XMD5, XSHA1) http://fireftp.mozdev.org/features.html</t>
<t>FTP Daemon (supports SITE CHECKMETHOD/SITE CHECKSUM) http://www.pro-bono-publico.de/projects/ftpd.html</t>
<t>FTP Voyager (supports XCRC) http://www.ftpvoyager.com/XCRC.asp</t>
<t>Gene6 FTP Server http://www.g6ftpserver.com/en/information#features</t>
<t>GlobalSCAPE's Secure FTP Server / EFT Server / CuteFTP clients (supports XCRC)</t>
<t>Globus FTP client / Globus Toolkit(supports CKSM) http://www.globus.org/toolkit/releasenotes/3.2.0/gridftp_notes.html</t>
<t>GoldenGate FTP (Ftp Full Java Server) (supports XCRC, XMD5, XSHA1)</t>
<t>IceWarp FTP Server http://www.icewarp.com/products/ftp_server/</t>
<t>ICS FTP client (supports XCRC, XMD5) http://www.magsys.co.uk/delphi/magics.asp</t>
<t>ioFTPD (supports XCRC)</t>
<t>JAFS (supports XCRC and MD5) http://www.sbbi.net/site/jafs/features.html</t>
<t>Kellerman FTP (supports XCRC) http://sharptoolbox.com/tools/kellerman-ftp</t>
<t>Limagito FTP server (supports XCRC, XMD5, XSHA1) http://www.limagito.com/file-mover-features.html</t>
<t>MOVEit DMZ (supports XSHA1)</t>
<t>Nofeel FTP server (supports XCRC, XMD5, XSHA1) http://www.nftpserver.com/history.php</t>
<t>Null FTP (supports XCRC, XMD5, XSHA) http://www.sharewareconnection.com/null-ftp-client-pro.htm</t>
<t>Orenosv FTP Client (supports XCRC, XMD5) http://www.orenosv.com/orenosv/ftpcli_en.html</t>
<t>ProFTPD module mod_digest (supports XCRC, XMD5, XSHA1, SHA256) http://www.smartftp.com/oss/proftpd/mod_digest.html</t>
<t>PSFTPd Secure FTP Server (supports XCRC, XMD5, XSHA) http://www.psftp.de/psftpd_fo.php</t>
<t>Quick 'n Easy FTP Server (supports XCRC) http://www.pablosoftwaresolutions.com/html/quick__n_easy_ftp_server_pro.html</t>
<t>RaidenFTPD32 FTP server (supports XCRC, XMD5)</t>
<t>Robo-FTP Server (supports XCRC, XMD5, XSHA1) http://kb.robo-ftp.com/change_log/show/61</t>
<t>SyncBackPro and SyncBackSE (supports XCRC) http://www.2brightsparks.com/syncback/sbpro-changes.html</t>
<t>Secure FTP Factory (supports XCRC)</t>
<t>Serv-U FTP Server (supports XCRC) http://www.serv-u.com/help/serv_u_help/additional_ftp_commands_supported_by_serv_u.htm</t>
<t>SmartFTP client (supports XCRC, XMD5, XSHA, CKSM) http://www.smartftp.com/features/</t>
<t>Starksoft Ftp Component for .NET / Mono (supports XCRC, XMD5, XSHA1) http://www.starksoft.com/prod_ftp.html</t>
<t>Titan FTP Server (supports XCRC)</t>
<t>Turbo FTP (supports XCRC)</t>
<t>WISE-FTP (supports XCRC) http://www.wise-ftp.com/news/</t>
<t>WS_FTP client / server (supports XSHA1, server also XMD5, XSHA1, XSHA256, XSHA512) http://ipswitchft.custhelp.com/app/answers/detail/a_id/671/kw/xmd5/r_id/166/sno/1</t>
<t>wuftpd (supports SITE CHECKMETHOD/SITE CHECKSUM)</t>
<t>wzdFTPd (supports XCRC, XMD5) http://www.wzdftpd.net/wiki/index.php/Commands</t>
<t>Zalman FTP Client (supports XCRC) http://www.zalmansoftware.com/download.html</t>
<t>zFTPServer</t>
	    </list></t>

	    </section>
	  

		


	    <section title="Document History">
		<t>[[ to be removed by the RFC editor before publication as an RFC. ]]</t>
		<t>Known issues concerning this draft:
	    <list style="symbols"> 
	      
		  <t>Should HASH support partial file hashes, similar to the Content-MD5 HTTP Header.</t>
		  <t>Underspecification of the representation of the file that shall undergo the hash calculation.</t>
		  <t>Should the server response include the algorithm? i.e. "S&gt; 213 SHA-256 xxxxxxxxxxxxxxx"</t>

	    </list></t>

<t>-04 : June 11, 2010.
	    
	    <list style="symbols">

          <t>User-PI usage and command errors sections updated.</t>
	    </list></t>

<t>-03 : May 21, 2010.
	    
	    <list style="symbols">

          <t>List of non-standard checksum and hash commands and their implementations.</t>
	    </list></t>

<t>-02 : April 16, 2010.
	    
	    <list style="symbols">

          <t>Error codes section.</t>
	    </list></t>

<t>-01 : April 7, 2010.
	    
	    <list style="symbols">

          <t>Changing HASH algorithm with OPTS.</t>
	      <t>Reference RFC 5797 and add IANA Considerations section.</t>	
	      <t>Informative Reference to expired Internet Draft (draft-twine-ftpmd5) which attempted to address this issue (it only supported one hash, MD5).</t>
	    </list></t>
		
<t>-00 : October 19, 2009.
	    
	    <list style="symbols">

	      <t>Initial draft.</t>
	    </list></t>
		
	    </section>
	  </back> 
	</rfc>