<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?rfc linefile="1:draft-bryan-ftp-hash-01.xml"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc
  PUBLIC "" "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-bryan-ftp-hash-01" ipr="trust200902">
    <front>        
      <title abbrev="FTP Extensions for Cryptographic Hashes">FTP Extensions for Cryptographic Hashes</title>
      <author initials="A." surname="Bryan" fullname="Anthony Bryan">
	    <organization></organization>
	    <address>
		  <postal>
			<street></street>
		    <city>Pompano Beach</city>
			<region>FL</region>
			<country>USA</country>
		  </postal>
	      <email>anthonybryan@gmail.com</email>
	      <uri>http://www.metalinker.org</uri>
	    </address>
      </author>
      <author initials="T." surname="Kosse" fullname="Tim Kosse">
	    <organization></organization>
	    <address>
	      <email>tim.kosse@filezilla-project.org</email>
	      <uri>http://filezilla-project.org/</uri>
	    </address>
      </author>
      <author initials="D." surname="Stenberg" fullname="Daniel Stenberg">
	    <organization></organization>
	    <address>
	      <email>daniel@haxx.se</email>
	      <uri>http://www.haxx.se/</uri>
	    </address>
      </author>
	<date year="2010"/>        

      <abstract>
	<t>The File Transfer Protocol does not offer any method to verify the integrity of a transferred file, nor can two files be compared against each other without actually transferring them first. Cryptographic hashes are a possible solution to this problem. In the past, several attempts have been made to add commands to obtain checksums and hashes,
       however none have been formally specified, leading to non-interoperability and confusion. To solve these issues, this document specifies a new FTP command to be used by clients to request cryptographic hashes of files.
</t>
      </abstract>    
	  
  </front>    

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
	<t>The File Transfer Protocol <xref target="RFC0959"/> does not offer any method to verify the integrity of a transferred file, nor can two files be compared against each other without actually transferring them first. Cryptographic hashes are a possible solution to this problem. In the past, several attempts have been made to add commands to obtain checksums and hashes,
       however none have been formally specified, leading to non-interoperability and confusion. To solve these issues, this document specifies a new FTP command to be used by clients to request cryptographic hashes of files.
HTTP has a similar feature named Instance Digests <xref target="RFC3230"/> which allows a client to request the cryptographic hash of a file.</t>

      <t>[[ Discussion of this draft should take place on
      apps-discuss@ietf.org. ]]</t>
	  
      <section title="Examples"><t><figure> 
	  <preamble>Example of HASH client request:</preamble>
	  
	  <artwork type="example">
        HASH filename.ext
</artwork></figure></t>

<t><figure> 
	  <preamble>HASH server response with Positive Completion code and the requested hash using the currently selected algorithm:</preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">
        213 80bc95fd391772fa61c91ed68567f0980bb45fd9
</artwork></figure></t>
	  
    </section>
	</section>

      <section title="Notational Conventions"> 

	<t>This specification describes conformance of FTP Extensions for cryptographic hashes.</t>
     

	<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
	"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
	document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14, <xref target="RFC2119"/>, as scoped to those conformance targets.</t>
	
	<t>This document also uses notation defined in STD 9, <xref target="RFC0959"/>.</t>
	
	<t>Syntax required is defined using the Augmented BNF defined in <xref target="RFC5234"/>.</t>

      </section>

	  
<section title="The HASH Command (HASH)" anchor="HASH">
<t>The HASH command allows for requesting the cryptographic hash of a file.</t>
<t>The syntax for the HASH command is:

<figure> 
	  <preamble></preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">
        hash = "HASH" SP &lt;pathname&gt;
</artwork></figure></t>
   
<t>As with all FTP commands, the "HASH" command label is interpreted in a case-insensitive manner.</t>
   
<t>The HASH command keyword MUST be followed by a single space (ASCII 32) followed by the pathname.</t>

<t>The pathname argument should reference the same file as other file based commands such as STOR or RETR which the same argument would reference.</t>

<t>The text returned in response to the HASH command MUST be:</t>

<t><figure> 
	  <preamble></preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">
        hash-response = "213" SP 1*HEXDIGIT CRLF
</artwork></figure></t>

<t>All hash values MUST be encoded in lowercase hexadecimal format.</t>

<t>The standard negative error codes 500 and 501 are sufficient to handle all errors involving the HASH command (e.g., syntax errors). Response code 550 is used if the file can not be found. Response code 552 is used if the user isn't allowed to use the HASH command.
Response code 450 is used to indicate the server is busy, e.g. already hashing other files yet inviting the client to retry in future.</t>

<t>The HASH command is useful for files transmitted in Image type mode (TYPE I) and Stream transfer mode (MODE S).</t>

<section title="FEAT response for HASH">

<t>A server that supports HASH should advertise it in FEAT response <xref target="RFC2389"/> with a list of all supported hash algorithms in a semicolon separated list. The hash algorithm that is currently selected is marked with an asterisk. In the example below, the "C>" lines are commands from user-PI to server-PI, the "S>" lines are server-PI replies. </t>

<t><figure> 
	  <preamble></preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">
        C&gt; feat
        S&gt; 211-Extensions supported:
        S&gt;  SIZE
        S&gt;  COMPRESSION
        S&gt;  HASH SHA-1*;MD5
        S&gt;  MDTM
        S&gt; 211 END
</artwork></figure></t>

<t>The IANA registry named "Hash Function Textual Names" defines values for hash types. Hash names should be presented in uppercase, but comparisons should be case-insensitive, e.g. MD5, md5, Md5 are all the same.</t>

<t><figure> 
	  <preamble></preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">	
        hash-feat = SP "HASH" SP hashlist CRLF
        hashlist = 1*( hashname ["*"] ";" )
        hashtype = 1*( hchar )
        hchar = ALPHA / DIGIT / "-" / "_" / "/" / "." / ","

</artwork></figure></t>

</section>

<section title="Changing the HASH algorithm">

	<t>To query the current hash algorithm and to change it, the OPTS command as defined in <xref target="RFC2389"/> is used with HASH as the first argument. If no second argument is passed, OPTS HASH simply returns the currently selected hash algorithm. To change the algorithm, a valid hashtype has to be given as second argument. If the command is successful, all future calls to HASH until the next successful OPTS HASH command or until the session is reinitialized (REIN) will use the selected hash algorithm.</t>
	
<t><figure>
	  <preamble></preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">
        C&gt; OPTS HASH
        S&gt; 200 SHA-1
        C&gt; OPTS HASH SHA-512
        S&gt; 200 SHA-512
        C&gt; OPTS HASH CRC-37
        S&gt; 501 Unknown algorithm, current selection not changed
</artwork></figure></t>

<t><figure> 
	  <preamble></preamble>
	  <artwork type="example">	
        hashopts-cmd = "OPTS HASH" [ SP hashtype ] CRLF
        hashopts-response = "200" SP hashtype CRLF
</artwork></figure></t>

</section>

</section>
<section title="Command Usage">
<t>Client requests the cryptographic hash of a file with HASH command. Server replies with cryptographic hash of file. Client downloads file. Client hashes the downloaded file and compares its hash to the hash obtained from the server. This command could also be used to verify that an uploaded file is an exact copy.</t>

</section>

	<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="IANA">
	<t>This new command is added to the "FTP Commands and Extensions" registry created by <xref target="RFC5797"/>.</t>
	<t>Command Name: HASH</t>
	<t>Description: Cryptographic Hash of a file</t>
	<t>FEAT String: HASH</t>
	<t>Command Type: Service execution</t>
	<t>Conformance Requirements: Optional</t>
	<t>Reference: This specification</t>


   
	</section>

<section title="Implementation Requirements">

	<t>All conforming implementations MUST at least support the SHA-1 algorithm. Implementations SHOULD NOT make any algorithm the default that is known to be weaker than SHA-1. Support for any additional algorithms is optional.</t>


	</section>
	
	  <section title="Security Considerations">

<t>Calculating a file's hash is a CPU intensive operation and can easily
consume the available disk I/O resources. If the HASH command isn't
implemented carefully, a server could be vulnerable to a denial of
service attack. On an affected server a malicious user could, for example,
continuously send HASH commands over multiple connections and thus
consume most of the FTP server's CPU and disk I/O resources, leaving little room for other
operations.
To mitigate this risk, a server SHOULD cache the calculated hashes so
that the hash of a file is only calculated once even if multiple hash
requests are sent for that file.</t>

<t>The performance of commonly used hard disk drives is adversely affected
by the amount of time the device needs to reposition its read-and-write
heads. A server SHOULD therefore avoid hashing multiple files at the
same time which are located on the same physical media and SHOULD
instead hash them sequentially. A possible solution is to use the 450
reply code of HASH to indicate that the server is already busy with
another HASH operation.</t>

<t>In addition, the HASH command can be used to draw conclusions about the
contents of a file. If the hash of a file on some server matches the
hash of some known, local file, both files are likely identical. To
prevent this scenario it suffices to limit use of the HASH command to
users who would already be able to download the file.</t>
		
	  </section>
	  


	</middle> 

	<back> 
	  
	  <references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor="RFC0959">

<front>
<title>File Transfer Protocol</title>
<author initials="J." surname="Postel" fullname="J. Postel">
<organization/></author>
<author initials="J." surname="Reynolds" fullname="J. Reynolds">
<organization/></author>
<date year="1985" month="October"/></front>

<seriesInfo name="STD" value="9"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="0959"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC2119">

<front>
<title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
<organization>Harvard University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
<street>Cambridge</street>
<street>MA 02138</street></postal>
<phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
<email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address></author>
<date year="1997" month="March"/>
<area>General</area>
<keyword>keyword</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
   In many standards track documents several words are used to signify
   the requirements in the specification.  These words are often
   capitalized.  This document defines these words as they should be
   interpreted in IETF documents.  Authors who follow these guidelines
   should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document:

<list>
<t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      RFC 2119.
</t></list></t>
<t>
   Note that the force of these words is modified by the requirement
   level of the document in which they are used.
</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC2389">

<front>
<title>Feature negotiation mechanism for the File Transfer Protocol</title>
<author initials="P." surname="Hethmon" fullname="P. Hethmon">
<organization/></author>
<author initials="R." surname="Elz" fullname="R. Elz">
<organization/></author>
<date year="1998" month="August"/></front>

<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2389"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC5234">

<front>
<title>Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title>
<author initials="D." surname="Crocker" fullname="D. Crocker">
<organization/></author>
<author initials="P." surname="Overell" fullname="P. Overell">
<organization/></author>
<date year="2008" month="January"/></front>

<seriesInfo name="STD" value="68"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5234"/>
</reference>


	  </references>


	  <references title="Informative References">

<reference anchor="RFC3230">

<front>
<title>Instance Digests in HTTP</title>
<author initials="J." surname="Mogul" fullname="J. Mogul">
<organization/></author>
<author initials="A." surname="Van Hoff" fullname="A. Van Hoff">
<organization/></author>
<date year="2002" month="January"/></front>

<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3230"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC5797">

<front>
<title>FTP Command and Extension Registry</title>
<author initials="J." surname="Klensin" fullname="J. Klensin">
<organization/></author>
<author initials="A." surname="Hoenes" fullname="A. Hoenes">
<organization/></author>
<date year="2010" month="March"/></front>

<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5797"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="draft-twine-ftpmd5">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="The MD5 and MMD5 FTP Command Extensions">The MD5 and MMD5 FTP Command Extensions</title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Twine" fullname="James Twine">
	  <organization></organization>
      <address><email>jtwine@jrtwine.com</email></address>
    </author>
    <date month="May" year="2002"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-twine-ftpmd5-00"/>
</reference>

	    </references> 

	    <section title="Acknowledgements and Contributors">
		  <t>Thanks to John C. Klensin, Alfred Hoenes, Daniel Stenberg, and James Twine.</t>
    </section>

	    <section title="List of Implementations with Non-standard Cryptographic Hash Command">
		<t>[[ to be removed by the RFC editor before publication as an RFC. ]]</t>
<t>At least one previous Internet Draft <xref target="draft-twine-ftpmd5"/>	 attempted to address this issue (it only supported one hash, MD5).</t>
<t>An incomplete list of FTP clients and servers that have implemented multiple commands (XMD5, XSHA1, SITE SHOHASH, etc) that are not formally specified, leading to non-interoperability and confusion.</t>
	    <t>
	    <list style="symbols">

<t>Akamai NetStorage p17-18
http://pigdogslow.dyndns.org/NetStorage_UserGuide.pdf</t>
<t>Apache Ftp Server (supports draft-twine-ftpmd5) http://cwiki.apache.org/FTPSERVER/documentation.html</t>
<t>Cerberus FTP server
http://www.softpedia.com/progChangelog/Cerberus-FTP-Server-Changelog-1904.html</t>
<t>FileCOPA FTP Server
http://www.filecopa-ftpserver.com/features.html</t>
<t>FireFTP
http://fireftp.mozdev.org/features.html</t>
<t>Gene6 FTP Server
http://www.g6ftpserver.com/en/information#features</t>
<t>GoldenGate FTP (Ftp Full Java Server)</t>
<t>IceWarp FTP Server
http://www.icewarp.com/products/ftp_server/</t>
<t>JAFS
http://www.sbbi.net/site/jafs/features.html</t>
<t>MOVEit DMZ</t>
<t>Nofeel FTP server
http://www.nftpserver.com/history.php</t>
<t>Null FTP
http://www.sharewareconnection.com/null-ftp-client-pro.htm</t>
<t>ProFTPD module mod_digest
http://www.smartftp.com/oss/proftpd/mod_digest.html</t>
<t>SmartFTP client http://www.smartftp.com/features/</t>
<t>Starksoft Ftp Component for .NET / Mono
http://www.starksoft.com/prod_ftp.html</t>
<t>RaidenFTPD32 FTP server</t>
<t>WS_FTP client / server
http://ipswitchft.custhelp.com/app/answers/detail/a_id/671/kw/xmd5/r_id/166/sno/1</t>
<t>wuftpd ('SITE CHECKMETHOD' and 'SITE CHECKSUM')</t>
<t>zFTPServer</t>
	    </list></t>

	    </section>
	  

		


	    <section title="Document History">
		<t>[[ to be removed by the RFC editor before publication as an RFC. ]]</t>
		<t>Known issues concerning this draft:
	    <list style="symbols"> 
	      

		  <t>Local HASH command: "Toggles number sign (#) printing for each data block that is transferred."</t>
		  <t>Underspecification of the representation of the file that shall undergo the hash calculation.</t>
		  <t>Correct response code to use for completion and errors.</t>
		  <t>Need to include some more general advice on algorithms just in case algorithm X is found to be broken the day after this draft is released.</t>
		  <t>Possibly we should suggest that servers calculate the hash numbers in advance, like when the file gets uploaded to avoid the risk of this becoming a DOS-vector.</t>
		  <t>The FTP server's right to refuse to calculate the hash is of course important to help against DOS risks.</t>
		  <t>Partial file hashes.</t>

	    </list></t>

<t>-01 : April 7, 2010.
	    
	    <list style="symbols">

          <t>Changing HASH algorithm with OPTS.</t>
	      <t>Reference RFC 5797 and add IANA Considerations section.</t>	
	      <t>Informative Reference to expired Internet Draft (draft-twine-ftpmd5) which attempted to address this issue (it only supported one hash, MD5).</t>
	    </list></t>
		
<t>-00 : October 19, 2009.
	    
	    <list style="symbols">

	      <t>Initial draft.</t>
	    </list></t>
		
	    </section>
	  </back> 
	</rfc>